Guide to the Philippine documents, 1894-1899
Department of Special Collections
Philippine documents,
1894-1899
Special Collections M0155
.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Source unknown.
Scope and Content
Letters, papers, and documents for the years 1894, 1898, and 1899. Primarily official communications and documents of provincial and local military and civil officers of the Philippine Republic. The provinces of Cavite and Manila and the district of Caloocan appear most often. There are signatures of Emilio Aguinaldo and other top officials and a few Spanish period items.
Access Terms
Aguinaldo, Baldomero.; Aguinaldo y Famy, Emilio, 1869-; Araneta, Gregario.; Arevalo, Bonifacio.; Ariterino, Domingo.; Buencamino, Felipe.; Cortes, Doroteo.; Flores Y Flores, Ambrosio.; Higgins, Horace L.; Rodriguez y Luna, Joaquin.; Santos, Eulogio.; Philippines--History--1812-1898.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.; Philippines--Politics and government--1896-1898.
Container List
- Judicial Papers (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Case of Pelagio Santiago, accused by his wife of breaking the arms of her infant son, 1898-1899s. Emilio Aguinaldo, B. Agruinaldo, [Domingo Aritcrino], et al. In Tagalog and Spanish, 1
  - Case of D. Lucia Pascual Ragundies, sued by daughter-in-law for restitution of water buffaloes, 189-s. Joaquin Rodriguez, et al. In Tagalog and Spanish, 2
    Contains certificates of ownership and brands.
  - Accusation of Antonio Silverio as accomplice in murder of Alcalde of Mas, 1887, 3; Fragment, rough draft, 1 p. In Tagalog and Spanish.
  - Case of Apollonia Sanson, Nicolas Rivera, Fulgencio Martinez, & Feliciano Torres - passive resistance, 1898In Spanish. s. Joaguin Rodriguez, et al., 4; Fragment, rough draft, 1 p. In Tagalog and Spanish.
  - Petition of widow of D. Jose Lerma for tax remission, 1898In Spanish. s. Joaquin Rodriques, et al., 5; Fragment, rough draft, 1 p. In Tagalog and Spanish.
- Educational Papers (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General Order, Sept. 19, 1898Direct immediate establishment of elementary school for both sexes. Joaquin Rodriques, [A. Flore], 1
  - Petitions of Meliton de la Cruz re: position of primary master, location of primary school, and order foxomg salary of primary teachers, n.d., 2; 4 p.
  - Lists of pupils and their standings, n.d., 3
  - Loose pages from composition books, n.d., 4
  - Inventory of furniture and materials. Primary school in Tambolong, n.d., 5
- Army Records (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Gelacio Avellano, deserter, 1899s. Segundo Rodrigo, Martin Villarica, Alfonso Enriquez, et al., 1
  - Spanish prisoners: Francisco Lagarejo, Juan Grubes, & Isidoro Isaac, 1899s. Vicente Correa y Punzal, Jose Santos, et al., 2
  - Letters from Juez Instructor recommending release of prisoners. Order for release and notification of same, 1899, 3
  - Citizens of Barawain. Letter to President of Province complaining of soldier's treatment of townspeople, n.d., 4
  - Doctor [?]. Letter to Judge at Balacan re: wounds of a prisoner, n.d., 5
  - List of 39 prisoners taken, n.d., 6
  - Mess accounts: booklet, 1899, 7
  - First Battalion at Bulacan, 2nd. Company. Roll with partial copy, 1899s. Vicente Correa y Punzal, Jose Santos, et al., 8
  - First Battalion at Bulacan, 2nd. Company. Rolls returns, documents, etc., [ca. 1899]s. Vicente Correa y Punzal, Jose Santos, et al., 9 - 25
- Military Communications (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Telegrams, etc. mostly pertaining to Province of Cavite. Generall Estrella, Col. Anthony, Julio Infante, Ramon P. Santes, Salafranea, and a number of illegible signatures, 1899
- Ecclesiastical Papers (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Baptismal records. Barawain, Bulacan, n.d., 1
  - St. Vincent De Paul. Prayer, n.d.In Spanish and Tagalog, 2
  - Catechism, n.d., 3; 14 loose pages of copied passages.
- Ecclesiastical Papers (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Aguinaldo, E. Printed proclamation, 1898 July 5, 1
  - Lim y Garcia, Luis Agapito. Petition, n.d., 2
  - Lim y Garcia, Luis Agapito. Certificate of character, n.d., 3
  - Order re: authority of local governor to sign public documents, 1898 Oct.s. [A. Flores], Joaquin Rodriguez, 4
  - Order re: registration of individuals and their wealth, 1898s. Joaquin Rodriguez, A. Flores, et al., 5
  - Order re: local tax, 1898s. Joaquin Rodriguez, et al., 6
  - Paper re: local tax, 1898s. Joaquin Rodriguez, 7
  - Order re: organization of police, 1898s. Joaquin Rodriguez, [A. Flores], et al., 8
  - Paper re: cemeteries of Loma and Binondo, 1898s. Joaquin Rodriguez, et al., 9
  - Order re: inventory of concealed property of Spanish enemy, 1898s. Joaquin Rodriguez., 10
  - Paper re: appointing an inspector of animals for public market, n.d., 11
- Ecclesiastical Papers (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Caloocan, Manila, 1989
- Landed Property (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Contract form between hacienda owner and tenant, in Spanish and dialect, n.d., 1
  - Legal suit against Teodora Garcia & Andres Bustamante for possession of fishing "property", n.d.s. Joaquin Rodriguez, et al., 2
  - Papers re: rental of bishopric property, n.d.s. Joaquin Rodriquez, et al., 3
  - Application by Teodorieo Cleofas & Gabino Cadaing for certain land title, n.d.s. Joaquin Rodriquez, et al., 4
  - Division of land belonging to minors: draft, n.d., 5
  - Application for land title: draft, n.d., 6
- Railroad records (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Orders from the superintendent, letters re: railroad matters, reports on movement of trains. Signature: Horace L. Higgins, L. Moreno, [J. Makapunga?], et al. ca. 54 items.
- Spanish Period - Military & Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Transfer applications, n.d., 1; 4 d.
  - Application for postponement of hearing, n.d., 2
  - Order re: treatment of prisoners, n.d., 3
  - Duplicate papers re: pension, n.d., 4
- Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Letters, covers, small notebook, some printed matter, telegram book with various notes & signatures, lists, etc. Some in Spanish but mostly in dialect including Tagalog.
- Gold Mining Report (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Report re: "S. Enrique" mine, 1894. In Spanish, signed by numerous Spanish officials.